In this video and in
the video after this one, I
wanna tell you about some of
the practical tricks for making gradient descent work well.
In this video, I want to tell you about an idea called feature skill.
Here's the idea.
If you have a problem where you
have multiple features, if you
make sure that the features
are on a similar scale, by
which I mean make sure that
the different features take on
similar ranges of values,
then gradient descents can converge more quickly.
Concretely let's say you
have a problem with two features
where X1 is the size
of house and takes on values
between say zero to two thousand
and two is the number
of bedrooms, and maybe that takes
on values between one and five.
If you plot the contours of
the cos function J of theta,
then the contours may look
like this, where, let's see,
J of theta is a function
of parameters theta zero, theta one and theta two.
I'm going to ignore theta zero,
so let's about theta 0
and pretend as a function of
only theta 1 and theta
2, but if x1 can take on
them, you know, much larger range
of values and x2 It turns
out that the contours of the
cause function J of theta
can take on this very
very skewed elliptical shape, except
that with the so 2000 to
5 ratio, it can be even more secure.
So, this is very, very tall
and skinny ellipses, or these
very tall skinny ovals, can form
the contours of the cause function J of theta.
And if you run gradient descents
on this cos-function, your
gradients may end up
taking a long time and
can oscillate back and forth
and take a long time before it
can finally find its way to the global minimum.
In fact, you can imagine if these
contours are exaggerated even
more when you draw incredibly
skinny, tall skinny contours,
and it can be even more extreme
than, then, gradient descent
just have a much
harder time taking it's way,
meandering around, it can take
a long time to find this way to the global minimum.
In these settings, a useful
thing to do is to scale the features.
Concretely if you instead
define the feature X
one to be the size of
the house divided by two thousand,
and define X two to be
maybe the number of bedrooms divided
by five, then the
count well as of the
cost function J can become
much more, much less
skewed so the contours may look more like circles.
And if you run gradient
descent on a cost function like
this, then gradient descent,
you can show mathematically, you can
find a much more direct path
to the global minimum rather than taking
a much more convoluted path
where you're sort of trying to
follow a much more complicated
trajectory to get to the global minimum.
So, by scaling the features so
that there are, the consumer ranges of values.
In this example, we end up
with both features, X one
and X two, between zero and one.
You can wind up with an implementation of gradient descent.
They can convert much faster.
More generally, when we're performing
feature scaling, what we often
want to do is get every
feature into approximately a  -1
to +1 range and concretely,
your feature x0 is always equal to 1.
So, that's already in that range,
but you may end up dividing
other features by different numbers
to get them to this range.
The numbers -1 and +1 aren't too important.
So, if you have a feature,
x1 that winds up
being between zero and three, that's not a problem.
If you end up having a different
feature that winds being
between -2 and  + 0.5,
again, this is close enough
to minus one and plus one
that, you know, that's fine, and that's fine.
It's only if you have a
different feature, say X 3
that is between, that
ranges from -100 tp +100
, then, this is a
very different values than minus 1 and plus 1.
So, this might be a
less well-skilled feature and similarly,
if your features take on a
very, very small range of
values so if X 4
takes on values between minus
0.0001 and positive 0.0001, then
again this takes on a
much smaller range of values
than the minus one to plus one range.
And again I would consider this feature poorly scaled.
So you want the range of
values, you know, can be
bigger than plus or smaller
than plus one, but just
not much bigger, like plus
100 here, or too
much smaller like 0.00 one over there.
Different people have different rules of thumb.
But the one that I use is
that if a feature takes
on the range of values from
say minus three the plus
3 how you should think that should
be just fine, but maybe
it takes on much larger values
than plus 3 or minus 3
unless not to worry and if
it takes on values from say minus one-third to one-third.
You know, I think that's fine
too or 0 to one-third or minus one-third to 0.
I guess that's typical range of value sector 0 okay.
But it will take on a
much tinier range of values
like x4 here than gain on mine not to worry.
So, the take-home message
is don't worry if your
features are not exactly on
the same scale or exactly in the same range of values.
But so long as they're all
close enough to this gradient descent it should work okay.
In addition to dividing by
so that the maximum value when
performing feature scaling sometimes
people will also do what's called mean normalization.
And what I mean by
that is that you want
to take a feature Xi and replace
it with Xi minus new i
to make your features have approximately 0 mean.
And obviously we want
to apply this to the future
x zero, because the future
x zero is always equal to
one, so it cannot have an
average value of zero.
But it concretely for other
features if the range
of sizes of the house
takes on values between 0
to 2000 and if you know,
the average size of a
house is equal to
1000 then you might
use this formula.
Size, set the feature
X1 to the size minus
the average value divided by 2000
and similarly, on average
if your houses have
one to five bedrooms and if
on average a house has
two bedrooms then you might
use this formula to mean
normalize your second feature x2.
In both of these cases, you
therefore wind up with features x1 and x2.
They can take on values roughly
between minus .5 and positive .5.
Exactly not true - X2
can actually be slightly larger than .5 but, close enough.
And the more general rule is
that you might take a
feature X1 and replace
it with X1 minus mu1
over S1 where to
define these terms mu1 is
the average value of x1
in the training sets
and S1 is the
range of values of that
feature and by range, I
mean let's say the maximum
value minus the minimum
value or for those
of you that understand the deviation
of the variable is setting S1
to be the standard deviation of the variable would be fine, too.
But taking, you know, this max minus min would be fine.
And similarly for the second
feature, x2, you replace
x2 with this sort of
subtract the mean of the feature
and divide it by the range
of values meaning the max minus min.
And this sort of formula will
get your features, you know, maybe
not exactly, but maybe roughly
into these sorts of
ranges, and by the
way, for those of you that
are being super careful technically if
we're taking the range as max
minus min this five here will actually become a four.
So if max is 5
minus 1 then the range of
their own values is actually
equal to 4, but all of these
are approximate and any value
that gets the features into
anything close to these sorts of ranges will do fine.
And the feature scaling
doesn't have to be too exact,
in order to get gradient
descent to run quite a lot faster.
So, now you know
about feature scaling and if
you apply this simple trick, it
and make gradient descent run much
faster and converge in a lot fewer other iterations.
That was feature scaling.
In the next video, I'll tell
you about another trick to make
gradient descent work well in practice.