You now know about linear regression with multiple variables.
In this video, I wanna tell
you a bit about the choice
of features that you have and
how you can get different learning
algorithm, sometimes very powerful
ones by choosing appropriate features.
And in particular I also want
to tell you about polynomial regression allows
you to use the machinery of
linear regression to fit very
complicated, even very non-linear functions.
Let's take the example of predicting the price of the house.
Suppose you have two features,
the frontage of house and the depth of the house.
So, here's the picture of the house we're trying to sell.
So, the frontage is
defined as this distance
is basically the width
or the length of
how wide your lot
is if this that you
own, and the depth
of the house is how
deep your property is, so
there's a frontage, there's a depth.
called frontage and depth.
You might build a linear regression
model like this where frontage
is your first feature x1 and
your depth is your second
feature x2, but when you're
applying linear regression, you don't
necessarily have to use
just the features x1 and x2 that you're given.
What you can do is actually create new features by yourself.
So, if I want to predict
the price of a house, what I
might do instead is decide
that what really determines
the size of the house is
the area or the land area that I own.
So, I might create a new feature.
I'm just gonna call this feature
x which is frontage, times depth.
This is a multiplication symbol.
It's a frontage x depth because
this is the land area
that I own and I might
then select my hypothesis
as that using just
one feature which is my
land area, right?
Because the area of a
rectangle is you know,
the product of the length
of the size So, depending
on what insight you might have
into a particular problem, rather than
just taking the features [xx]
that we happen to have started
off with, sometimes by defining
new features you might actually get a better model.
Closely related to the
idea of choosing your features
is this idea called polynomial regression.
Let's say you have a housing price data set that looks like this.
Then there are a few different models you might fit to this.
One thing you could do is fit a quadratic model like this.
It doesn't look like a straight line fits this data very well.
So maybe you want to fit
a quadratic model like this
where you think the size, where
you think the price is a quadratic
function and maybe that'll
give you, you know, a fit
to the data that looks like that.
But then you may decide that your
quadratic model doesn't make sense
because of a quadratic function, eventually
this function comes back down
and well, we don't think housing
prices should go down when the size goes up too high.
So then maybe we might
choose a different polynomial model
and choose to use instead a
cubic function, and where
we have now a third-order term
and we fit that, maybe
we get this sort of
model, and maybe the
green line is a somewhat better fit
to the data cause it doesn't eventually come back down.
So how do we actually fit a model like this to our data?
Using the machinery of multivariant
linear regression, we can
do this with a pretty simple modification to our algorithm.
The form of the hypothesis we,
we know how the fit
looks like this, where we say
H of x is theta zero
plus theta one x one plus x two theta X3.
And if we want to
fit this cubic model that
I have boxed in green,
what we're saying is that
to predict the price of a
house, it's theta 0 plus theta
1 times the size of the house
plus theta 2 times the square size of the house.
So this term is equal to that term.
And then plus theta 3
times the cube of the
size of the house raises that third term.
In order to map these
two definitions to each other,
well, the natural way
to do that is to set
the first feature x one to
be the size of the house, and
set the second feature x two
to be the square of the size
of the house, and set the third feature x three to
be the cube of the size of the house.
And, just by choosing my
three features this way and
applying the machinery of linear
regression, I can fit this
model and end up with
a cubic fit to my data.
I just want to point out one
more thing, which is that
if you choose your features
like this, then feature scaling
becomes increasingly important.
So if the size of the
house ranges from one to
a thousand, so, you know,
from one to a thousand square
feet, say, then the size
squared of the house will
range from one to one
million, the square of
a thousand, and your third
feature x cubed, excuse me
you, your third feature x
three, which is the size
cubed of the house, will range
from one two ten to
the nine, and so these
three features take on very
different ranges of values, and
it's important to apply feature
scaling if you're using gradient
descent to get them into
comparable ranges of values.
Finally, here's one last example
of how you really have
broad choices in the features you use.
Earlier we talked about how a
quadratic model like this might
not be ideal because, you know,
maybe a quadratic model fits the
data okay, but the quadratic
function goes back down
and we really don't want, right,
housing prices that go down,
to predict that, as the size of housing freezes.
But rather than going to
a cubic model there, you
have, maybe, other choices of
features and there are many possible choices.
But just to give you another
example of a reasonable
choice, another reasonable choice
might be to say that the
price of a house is theta
zero plus theta one times
the size, and then plus theta
two times the square root of the size, right?
So the square root function is
this sort of function, and maybe
there will be some value of theta
one, theta two, theta three, that
will let you take this model
and, for the curve that looks
like that, and, you know,
goes up, but sort of flattens
out a bit and doesn't ever
come back down.
And, so, by having insight into, in
this case, the shape of a
square root function, and, into
the shape of the data, by choosing
different features, you can sometimes get better models.
In this video, we talked about polynomial regression.
That is, how to fit a
polynomial, like a quadratic function,
or a cubic function, to your data.
Was also throw out this idea,
that you have a choice in what
features to use, such as
that instead of using
the frontish and the depth
of the house, maybe, you can
multiply them together to get
a feature that captures the land area of a house.
In case this seems a little
bit bewildering, that with all
these different feature choices, so how do I decide what features to use.
Later in this class, we'll talk
about some algorithms were automatically
choosing what features are used,
so you can have an
algorithm look at the data
and automatically choose for you
whether you want to fit a
quadratic function, or a cubic function, or something else.
But, until we get to
those algorithms now I just
want you to be aware that
you have a choice in
what features to use, and
by designing different features
you can fit more complex functions
your data then just fitting a
straight line to the data and
in particular you can put polynomial
functions as well and sometimes
by appropriate insight into the
feature simply get a much
better model for your data.